[Music]
Stanford
University okay
let's let's go to um
the the SpaceTime view of string
theory what other what other kind of
view could there be but SpaceTime but I
mean let's let's think of the Blackboard
as space time and view what uh what
String Theory looks like first let's do
something simpler first let's just talk
about an ordinary particle an ordinary
particle in classical
mechanics has a
trajectory in nonre both in
non-relativistic physics and
relativistic physics the trajectory can
be described by the three-dimensional
position
X as a function of
T but if you're doing relativity there's
something which is more convenient and
that's to take all four
components space components and time
components of position call them X mu
and think of them as a function of a
variable which just denotes and demarks
let's say proper time along the
trajectory of to let to be the proper
time along the
trajectory and then clearly if you know
the four-dimensional position I at every
proper time or every every value of this
parameter here then you can say exactly
where the trajectory went so there's a
slight well maybe more than a slight
there's a a difference of emphasis in
non-relativistic physics where you think
of X as a function of time and in
relativistic physics where you might be
inclined to think of X mu the four
components of position as a function of
a parameter along the trajectory a kind
of Scala parameter along the trajectory
in each case the motion of a particle is
um defined by an action by a principle
of least action in the case of a
non-relativistic system for a free
particle forget potentials nothing else
the action which is usually called S I
don't know why it's called s it's the
same label as we use for entropy and to
make matters worse in many cases entropy
and action turn out to be the same thing
numerically but the S is action
and for a non-relativistic particle it's
the in or it's the integral over time
along the trajectory of the kinetic
energy 12 x do squared and I've chosen
the mass of the particle arbitrarily to
be one because I get tired of writing
it okay that's the uh that's the
action and what do you do with it you
minimize it you minimize it to find the
trajectory of the particle you minimize
it it subject to some end positions
holding down the end points you minimize
it now that's not what you do in quantum
mechanics in Quant or before we do that
let me uh let me discuss the
relativistic case in the relativistic
case something very similar the thing is
the action can be taken to be the
integral over to the proper time along
the trajectory of DX mu by D to DX mu by
D
to notice there's one upper index and
one lower index and you can figure out
that what that means in other words it
looks very very much like the
non-relativistic kinetic energy formula
but it means something different there
are four components of position and the
time is the uh the proper time and
what's more the time components and the
space components of this uh expression
have different sign but apart from that
they look very
similar uh and again what do you do with
it you minimize it you minimize it
subject to the constraint that the at
the ends of the period the particle is
at this SpaceTime point or that space
and that Spa SpaceTime point so there's
a a sort of parallel
structure and basic principle is a
principle of least action now in quantum
mechanics you do something totally
different with the
action what you do with the action you
ask a different question you don't ask
what is the trajectory given to end
points here you ask what is the
trajectory given to end
points the answer is of course a
straight
line in either case it's a straight line
it's straight line to space and
time uh with constant
velocity you ask a different question
you ask what is the
amplitude that a particle that started
at this point at Time Zero or at the
beginning of time at the start of the
time interval is detected at that point
at a later in at a later
time that's the question you ask you
don't ask what's the trajectory in
between you ask what's the amplitude for
the particle to go from here to here and
the answer
is the amplitude to go from0 one to
point 2 in either
case you write the action you write the
exponential of the action e to the I not
just any exponential but exponential
with an i in it e to the I times the
action let's write it out
explicitly d by DT over 12
DT DX by
[Music]
DT squared this integral here goes from
T1 to T2 but then you're not finished
you're not finished this expression I
depends not only on the position of the
particle over here and over here but it
depends on the position of the particle
everywhere in between so what do you do
with it to find the
amplitude you integrate or you sum over
all possible
trajectories some over all
trajectories
or integral strictly speaking over all
trajectories this is a monstrously
complicated thing it's not a simple
integral that you can put on
uh U what's his names
uh yeah
Mathematica it's an infinite dimensional
integral a continuously infinite
dimensional integral so it's a
mathematical monstrosity I mean
that uh but this this integral over here
is just the integral along the
trajectory that's easy that's just the
action but this integral over here is
the sum of all all trajectories so the
particle FS out all trajectories it
doesn't sample the one of least action
you integrate over all of them this
expression to find the amplitude to go
from 1 to two that's the quantum
mechanical uh version of the principle
of least action finding path integral
you do the same thing in either
classical mechan in either um
non-relativistic physics with this
expression or relativistic physics with
that
expression when you calculate in
relativistic physics the amplitude to go
from 1 to two is called the
propagator it's called the propagator
for the particle to go from one to two
and you do some fancier things with
it you for example consider processes
where particles come in join split and
go
out a similar kind
of action
is defined in terms of the action for
each one of these what should we call
these each one of these segments you add
the action together for each
segment and then you don't sum over just
a single trajectory you sum over all of
these trajectories and on top of
everything else you integrate over the
points where the trajectories came
together so you do the same kind of
thing and it gives you aing diagram
and then at the end to make the whole
thing even more complicated you sum over
all findan diagrams for a given process
and that gives you the amplitude not for
a particle to go from one point to
another but for a pair of particles to
come in and go
out all right that's the basic setup of
quantum of uh findan findan path
integrals before we go into String
Theory let me teach you a
trick that physicists use over and over
again it's a cheat it's a cheat can it
be justified in some special cases it
can be
justified uh it turns out it can be more
easily justified in string theory than
in uh than in Quantum than in uh Quantum
field Theory but I'll tell you what the
trick
is this kind of integral this one this
integral is some over the trajectories
it feels out all trajectories some of
let's take let's let's even concentrate
on a non-relativistic case it feels out
trajectories which go like this it feels
out trajectories which go like this it
feels out straight trajectories and it
feels out some wild wild insane
trajectories are some of them somehow
more important than others of course
they are the ones which correspond to
the classical motion the straight line
ones must be the most important ones
otherwise classical physics wouldn't
make
sense but when you look at the integrand
here e to the I times anything always
has magnitude what one so whatever the
trajectory is they all have equal
numerical weight they come in with
different
phases the different phases can cancel
each other if you're adding up numbers
on the complex plane and all those
numbers numbers happen to have unit
magnitude that doesn't mean they can't
cancel they can they can cancel they can
give rise to a real number they can give
rise to an imaginary number they can do
all sorts of things but each one of the
contributions is as big as every other
contribution in that
case a normal definition of an integral
doesn't make
sense it doesn't converge it doesn't
converge because the trajectories which
are wildly way out there and correspond
to some very very distant trajectories
in some sense don't have smaller and
smaller ampl
amplitude as the trajectory gets more
and more
wild so strictly speaking these path
integrals don't really exist as any well
studied mathematical objects okay so how
do we deal with them
well one way of dealing with them is to
be extremely careful Define integrals in
an extremely precise
way uh all sorts of reservations and
things that are too hard to even for the
people who do them to to to think about
really hard stuff there's a trick
there's a trick and the trick always
works the trick is one which to justify
it is as hard as trying to understand
the original integral but once you've
Justified it it's it's the trick which
always works and always gives you the
right answer so I'm going to tell you
what the trick is let's which shall we
take let's take this case here the
relativistic
case you change the tow
variable and how do you change it very
very
simply you invent a new variable called
S and S is just any number time to we'll
choose the number Alpha later to our
convenience it's just a change of
variables this is an integration
variable incidentally it goes from to 1
to to 2 where to 1 and to two are the
end points of the
trajectory but we change variables oh
this s we shouldn't confuse this s with
the action I'm sorry I even
called let's call the action let's give
the action another name in order to
avoid confusion
you have a little s big S what's the
difference you're
right little s okay little
s little s is by definition Alpha T and
what is alpha alpha is whatever you want
it to be we'll pick it later all right
so let's see what we get then d uh did I
want no I think I'm going to be smarter
I'm going to set c equal to Alpha *
s to is equal to Alpha then then I don't
have to invert the
equation uh all right so what does this
give us this gives us integral then from
S1 to S2 the end points now are the end
points of the S interval the end points
of the S interval are of course just
Alpha times the endpoint values for the
to
integration okay now we have D to DT is
Alpha
DS and then we have DX What's d d x by D
to in terms of DX by
DS wherever you see a tow you stick
Alpha Time s that's all so this becomes
DX by d
s
squared I won't bother writing all the
indices
mu but one over Alpha squared for each
for each tow I have to put an alpha s so
that gives me a one of alpha squ so
there's Alpha squ
downstairs that's the
action Alpha
downstairs now what do we do with that
action we put it up into the exponent
with an I can you read this e to the
I2 I suppose if I want to get it right
let's just put the 1/2 out here we keep
it out of the
way the I of course is just a constant
can be brought inside the
integral and it's I over
Alpha now it's complete
nonsense or at least it needs a major
justification to do this trick but what
are we going to choose what do you think
we're going to choose Alpha to
b i i or minus I
uh let's see I over I is one right
I think I want it to be minus
I that
sounds right I over I yeah I think I
want Alpha
equals I choose it to be minus I this
becomes I over minus I which is also
called minus
one and the whole in the whole
exponential magically loses its
I it becomes e to the
integral minus that's this minus sign
from I over minus I
12 DX by d
s
squared d
s the only
place that we've have to be a little bit
careful is we have to remember the end
points of the interval here are not
really real values of s we're going to
pretend that that s can be a a real
quantity that this integral can be
treated as a real
integral even though the end points of
the integral are not real numbers why
aren't they real numbers because to is
equal to minus i s and the end points of
the original integral were real values
of T to but let's forget that let's just
call it from S1 to S2 and later on we'll
remember that S1 and S two were
imaginary values later on for the moment
just leave it this
way now we're going to integrate this
over all
trajectories over all
trajectories this is much better than
the original
integral in the original integral no
matter how Wild the trajectory was the
amplitude for that particular trajectory
was in magnitude one now let's take some
wild
trajectory and stick it in here if the
trajectory is wild if it goes off and
extends off to some large spatial
separation and comes back then there's
going to be places where the X by the S
is going to be very
large if a trajectory is wild in any
form
whatever maybe just because so maybe it
doesn't even go very far maybe it just
Wiggles extremely rapidly
well that's okay the X by the S is going
to be very very large it's going to
oscillate but it's going to be very very
large or maybe it goes
off and then comes back a long distance
still the X by the S will be very very
large along the orbits where it goes out
and comes back so for any kind of
trajectory that's far from just the
simplest trajectory namely the straight
line
the action is going to be
huge it's going to be huge and it comes
in with a negative sign e to the minus a
large number is a small
number so in this form wild trajectories
don't contribute very much only
trajectories near the straight
trajectory are
important this is a form of path
integral that is used in statistical
mechanic it's called the weener
integral it was not it was invented
before the finding path
integral and it's perfectly convergent
mathematicians know how to define it in
a serious way and it's a good
quantity so this is what this is what we
are always doing we are always making
this trick of turning a Time variable on
its side by making it I times some time
interval time variable and then using it
in in integrals now what's what's the
trick though at the end of the day this
whole thing is going to be some
function of the end points of the
integral you evaluate this not paying
any attention to the fact that the end
points of the interval are imaginary
numbers but then after you have
evaluated
it you then
the right word is analytically continu
it or extrapolate to imaginary values of
uh of s this is something that we know
how to do it's uh it's a straightforward
procedure if you actually evaluate these
things for the experts they're analytic
functions of s and you can extrapolate
them or analytically continue them to
the desired complex points this is the
only real way that physicists ever
really do path integrals
when you hear people talking about path
integrals either they're just talking or
if they're actually trying to perform
them they're doing them this way by
turning the time variable on its
side all right I thought I would tell
you that once and for all because we're
going to do that in string theory
so let's come to string theory
now same same kind of setup but now a
particle is not a point it's a
string it's world history is not a world
line it's a
surface it could be open strings in
which case it's a surface a ribbon
kind of ribbon a ribbon that can change
its length and change its way it's
embedded in space but it's a ribbon
closed strings it's not a ribbon it's a
tube you can call it a world
tube usually called A World
sheet that's the motion of a
particle let's talk about its action
we're interested in this action now the
kind of question we're going to ask is
given the location of all of the points
on the string at some initial
time and some later time what's the
amplitude to go from the initial state
to the final State what's the amplitude
that if you set the string up in a
certain configuration and then let it go
that you would find it at a later time
at some other
configuration
now the location of a point on the
worldsheet is a function X of two
variables one of them is a kind of time
variable along the sheet we'll call it
to it's not real time it's a it's it's
real time no more real time than the to
variable up here was more like proper
time but now it's just a parameter it's
just a parameter you take the
sheet you coordinati it
with two coordinates Sigma and
to and you write X of to and sigma we've
done that
before it's a function of two
variables if you know X mu for each
Sigma and to then you know where that
point on the string is and if you're
given the whole history of the string as
a x mu of Sigma and to that that does it
that's the whole history again you
construct an
action again you construct an action and
this time the action is the immediate
generalization of that but with two
independent variables here it's s is
equal to
integral from I'm not going to I'm not
going to try to label the starting uh
it's too complicated to to label the
start and the finish we'll just write
what it is it's the integral
d d Sigma it's an integral over the
two-dimensional worldsheet
of d x
mu by d c^
squ uh
yes
minus DX
mu by D Sigma
S I think I have it
right the X mu by the t^ 2 minus the X
mu by the sigma squ that's the action
for the string and notice this is the
action of a field moving in town Sigma
space it's just the action of The
Wiggles moving up and down the to Sigma
the tow and sigma but it is also the
action for a tube moving through
SpaceTime uh comes from the fact that
TOS uh comes from the same
place okay it comes from kinetic energy
minus potential energy
kinetic energy minus potential energy
this is kinetic it's like a Time
derivative this is potential energy it's
like a space derivative so it's the fact
that the action lran has a minus sign T
minus
V
okay what do you do with this action you
exponentiate it e to the
I and then you integrate it over all
possible possible
surfaces I'm not going to try to draw a
complicated surface well I tried I
failed um you integrate it or sum it
over all possible
surfaces
incidentally there's a classical version
where you don't do the path integral
which just tells you if you start the
string in a certain fashion and end it
in a certain fashion how it has to move
in between to satisfy classical
equations of motion to go from the
initial to the final but we're not
interested in that we're interested in
quantum mechanics this is the amplitude
for the string to go from an initial
configuration to a final configuration
that's the setup that's the uh if you
like after all is said and done this can
pretty much be defined to be the
definition of string theory well no it
that's too
simple you can generalize is the
idea you say supposing I'm not
interested in a string going to a string
but two strings going to two strings or
two strings going to three strings then
you can generalize it by starting with
two strings ending with three
strings and drawing all the possible
surfaces that can interpolate in between
them
there's a surface that interpolates
between them there are other surfaces
which interpolate between them with
different topology you can put a hole in
here perfectly legitimate but let's
concentrate on the ones without holes in
them for the
moment you can then ask the question
what is the amplitude to start with two
strings each one in its own given
configuration
and end up with three strings also in
particular configuration the answer is
the
same the answer is e to the I times the
integral over all surfaces which connect
the initial state to the final State e
to the
I integral over all surfaces of the
action for that
surface in this simple case say an
electron going from 1 Point to another
is VX C Sigma zero so doesn't change you
mean a point electron yeah particle does
Point electron if you were dealing with
it by find Min integrals before anybody
heard of string theory you would you
wouldn't have any Sigma you would just
have to right uh I think maybe you're
asking whether in some limit or other
this reduces to the uh yeah yeah that is
a good question the answer is yes uh as
long as the electron is very much
lighter than the string scale and as
long as the uh energies of the processes
are low then yeah these things will um
will reproduce finan diagrams ordinary
finan
diagrams so yeah they uh they are
connected that would take us uh more
than a little bit okay so that's
the that's practically the definition of
string theory incidentally if you really
mean some over all surfaces that connect
them including the surfaces that have
holes in them of various
kinds then that's pretty much the analog
of summing over all Fineman diagrams
with all possible topologies and all
possible number of loops and so
forth so you're having one simple
expression or one simple idea the sum
over surfaces you have something which
is as complex or as complex is perhaps
not the right word it's much simpler
than finding diagrams in many
ways
uh but it contains as much the same kind
of information as the sum of all finding
diagrams would
contain okay but let's forget these
holes for the moment and just
concentrate on the structure of this
path integral here there's a path
integral for
Strings again it's a monstrosity for the
same
reason wildly varying surfaces
contribute as heavily
as straight surfaces and so forth the
integral doesn't converge in any
meaningful sense because again surfaces
which stretch out to Alpha Centurion
come back are no less numerically large
in the amplitude than a nice simple
tube all right so that means we've got
to do something to make this integral
make
sense you can do what a serious
mathematician would do would be to try
to define a new kind of integral people
have studied that or you can do what a
physicist uh would do and say
analytically
continue analytically continue last
Refuge of
Scoundrels okay and we are going to be
Scoundrels what do we do not we don't
worry about Sigma Sigma is uh is um not
our problem it's actually to which is
our problem as we will see
um let's do the same
thing let's let to go to it to now I'm
not going to call it s I'm not going to
call it s so we'll just get too many
variables I'm just going to tell you we
now make a transformation of variables
from TOA to it
to same trick when you do you'll pick up
an ie from here and you will pick up two
eyes from
here you won't pick up up any eyes over
here so let's follow it each time you
see the a tow you you write I
to really too is becoming s but I don't
want to introduce another uh another
variable so I'm just going to say to
goes to I to we change variables to it
to then the first thing that happens is
we pick up an i over
here that's good because it'll get rid
of this ey but then we pick up two i's
down
here what is two
i's minus so that turns this into minus
here same as the minus
here and gets rid of the I over here now
unfortunately I didn't really mean it
when I said to goes to I to I meant to
goes to minus I to in which case we have
an extra minus sign here same as for the
particle
case now look at what we have we have
something oh uh no I I yeah you just no
I too many minus
signs too many minus signs I've lost
control of the calculation no no you had
I squ yeah okay that gives you one minus
one oh yeah you had minus I squ so you
end up with Plus signs over there and
plus sign here uh minus sign where here
oh
no whichever one you want you can get it
whichever one you want you can get so
let's let's get this
one let's get that one it's either to
equals goes to minus I to or to goes to
plus I to the reason I want the plus
sign here and the minus signs here is
because that allows me to move remove
the minus signs here and put it out here
now why is that a good thing to
do it's a good thing to do because what
appears in here is
positive the more wild the surface is
the bigger it's going to
be even if the surface doesn't fluctuate
out to far distances but it just
vibrates a lot then the XD tow or the or
Wiggles too much then if it Wiggles too
much the XD Sigma will be large if it
vibrates too much the XD tow will be
large if it stretches out to Alpha
centuri both of them are going to be
large and
positive so one good thing of this trick
is it made these both of the same sign
and both positive and then e to a minus
a positive number is
small or a large positive number so what
does this do it does the same thing that
um it did in the particle case it
suppresses the wildly varying surfaces
and it allows you to actually calculate
the path
integral I should tell you there's
another form of string theory and where
what you put in for the action is is
more complicated but quite
beautiful it's
actually for both the particle and the
string there are other forms of the
action which are mathematically harder
to deal with but in the certain sense um
geometrically very very highly Mo
motivated for the case of the
particle what you put in is the proper
path length as the action the action is
just the proper path length between the
initial point and the final point the
proper path length itself and for the um
for the string what you put in is the
SpaceTime area of the world sheet that's
another setup another formal way to do
it gives you the same answers and uh but
it is more complicated so I'm not going
to do
it if you ever come across the term
nambo goo action the nambo goo action is
the action which just says stick in for
the action the area of the uh of the
world
sheet the other form is sometimes called
a poov action although it had nothing to
do with poov it was invented by
me which Paul Yakov constantly keeps
telling
people people like to get credit but
they they like to get credit for what
they did
so uh anyway it's called a poliu action
this action here things are named after
people who didn't do them much more
often he did do something else which is
related to this but um but that's but
that the other thing he did which is
closely related to this there some other
factors in it which is also quite
beautiful which was invented by poov
it's called the leeville
action Leo was a mathematician who died
long long before even classical
mechanics was invented so don't
ask same reason that Pinsky brains are
called derish brains I don't know
that
aroundin I I guess jury
shap uh strings were around a long
time dur boundary conditions on ordinary
strings were around a long time
yeah right that's
correct
okay that is the idea of the path
integral
for string theory now I want to explain
some
mathematics some
uh trivial math not trivial it's nice
mathematics many of you have seen it
before let's
see
oh
yeah let's take a look at this action
and ask what it's what it's um what are
the things that it's inv
under what are the things that it's
invariant under what kind of
transformations in particular of Sigma
and
to into new variables is an invariant
why am I interested in that well I never
told you
exactly what the choice of Sigma and to
were I didn't tell you how to choose
Sigma and too on here just draw it any
way we
please surely the answer can't be the
same for any choice of Sigma and to
there must be some rules about what kind
of coordinates I can use on the
worldsheet
but Al those rules rigid they tell you
you have to use these particular
coordinates or is there some
invariance which allows you to um to
have a variety of different uh sets of
coordinates which will all give you the
same
answer there's the classic problem of
the invariances of a lonian what are the
invariances of this SL grangian but in
particular what are the invariances with
respect to coordinate transformations of
the sigma toau surface of the sigma
parameters Sigma TOS are just labels of
points they don't have any independent
meaning other than just labels of points
this one is called George this one's
called Fred this one's called
Harvey clearly the answer can't depend
on whether I rename the points
um uh Melvin whatever
okay
so uh what are the
invariances that
uh that are
allowed so we look at this action and we
ask what kind of what kind of
Transformations can we
make let's look at it in a little more
detail here it
is the X by in fact instead of looking
at the
um at the action itself let's look at
the equation of motion which would come
by varying this action why it's just
it's it's as good as looking at the
action the equation of motion that would
come from varing this action would look
like a wave equation this is basically
the action for a wave equation with one
exception what's the
exception the sign
here yeah two positive signs okay what's
a wave equation a wave equation would be
DC X by D to^
2 minus DC X by D Sigma squared equals
z what do you think the equation of
motion coming from the from uh from uh
from this would
be
plus X is some field on the to Sigma
coordinate space do you know the name of
this equation it's not called the wave
equation the Lao equation
two-dimensional llao equation it's the
two-dimensional Appo equation DC of
something with respect to one variable
squar plus DC usually you see it in a
different form you see the the variable
X would be replaced by fi some function
maybe just F
function and to and sigma would be
called X and Y so You' have an equation
like DC F what DC fi actually yeah by
dx2 plus DC F by D y^
2 equals
zero in two dimensions in three
dimensions you would add another one DC
Pi by dz^2 I'm talking now not about
physics I'm talking about the formal
structure of equations you recognize
this
equation yeah
vibrating Dr no no
okay I don't want to get into yeah
you're partly right but uh a vibrating
drum also has a Time variable in it okay
so I don't want to get into vibrating
drums but you're you're not completely
wrong
um is equation for the electrostatic
potential except on the electrostatic
potential you would have a a charge
density on the right hand
side okay that's
called it's called a llao
equation and now it's a Lael equation in
two
Dimensions except now the variable fi is
replaced by X and the variable X and Y
are replaced by to and sigma but
otherwise the mathematical structure of
this equation is the
same and question is Yeah question you
have second deres say you have first
derivatives here you have first here
first derivatives yeah but when you have
first derivatives in an
action it gives you second derivatives
in the equation of motion just like
having X do squared in an action gives
you xou dot in the equation so that's a
good question okay and whether I work
with the action or the equation of
motion it doesn't matter you get the six
of one half a dozen of the other all
right uh I just like this form better
because it helps me illustrate a a point
all right now let's what is a second
derivative second derivative of x think
of the tow axis as being discrete now
just uh to give you a geometric picture
of what this equation means think of the
to axis as being discret with little
separations Epsilon between the
neighboring
points what is a first derivative a
first derivative is let's call this
point one let's go one two and
three a first derivative is closely
related to the difference of a quantity
at neighboring
points right so the first
derivative would be like X of 3 - x of
2 you divide it by Epsilon but uh this
is not the important thing let's divide
it by Epsilon Epsilon is a distance
between the points and then you let the
Epsilon go to zero and that gives you
the first
derivative let's not worry about the
epsilons right now that's not the point
a first derivative is like the
difference of something at neighboring
points if that's what a first derivative
is what is a second derivative a second
derivative is difference of first
derivatives all right so a second
derivative is x3 -
X2 that's the first derivative evaluated
between these two points minus the first
derivative evaluated one step over so
that's
minus X of 2 - x of
1 that's the analog the discrete analog
of the second derivative let's see what
it is
it's
uh X3 X of
3 plus X of
1 minus
twice X of
2 so what is
it it's the sum of the
quantities on the outer edges minus
twice the quantity in the center
that's a second
derivative let's look at the thing which
occurs in the lass equation here instead
of taking the to axis to be discrete
let's take the to Sigma plane to be
discret the to Sigma plane is discreet
now and let's see if we can
geometrically identify what this
equation
means let's go to a point over here a
point over here the second derivative of
x with respect to
too is X at this point plus X at this
point minus tce X at the center that's
what we just figured out let's label the
points 1 2 3 4 and at the center we'll
call
five so DC X by D to^ 2 that's X of 1 +
x of 3 - t x of 5 right
how about the second x with respect to
Sigma
squar oh did I sorry did I make a
mistake
here okay it depends on which way I
think of Tao and sigma I guess I have in
this picture here I guess I have ta
going horizontally and sigma going
vertically I don't usually think of it
about it that way but that's all right
so X
the second derivative with respect to to
is this one plus this one minus this one
how about the second derivative with
respect to
Sigma that's going to be this one plus
this one minus t x of
5 so we get to add in plus X of
2 plus X of
4 - t x of 5
equals
z well that's not so bad X of 1 plus X
of 3 plus X of 4 plus X of 2 x of 1 3 2
and four so we get the
sum of the x's on the points surrounding
X of
five minus 4 * the sum Sorry 4 * X at 5
equal 0 another way to say it is
that X of 1 plus X of
2 plus X of 3 plus X of
equals 4X at
5 4X at
5 or you know another way to say it is
that X at 5 is the average of the
x's
on that's what the lass equation says
it's true in higher Dimensions also okay
that's what the lass equation says that
at any point if you surround it by a
square and even though this thing is on
its side it is a square any Square any
small square any infinite decimal
square that if you evaluate the field
at the sum the sum of the field at the
uh at the
corners that the field at the center is
the average at the corners now the
square doesn't have to be oriented this
way it's well known that this equation
is invariant under rotations of the
sigma to
plane so you can say it even more
geometrically take any
Square any Square oriented in any way
any small square this is of course only
true for infinite decimal
squares for any small infinite decimal
Square the field at the center is the
average of the field at the corners
that's an invariant way apart from the
fact that you have to think about limits
which makes it a little more complicated
apart from that limiting procedure that
you have to do that's an invariant way
to say what the what the lass equation
is and it's an variant way to describe
the equation of motion the classical
equation of motion of this of this uh
this thing
here okay so now I can tell you exactly
what the
invariance structure of the lass
equation or of this action is it's the
class of transformations of the sigma
tow
plane which take every infinitesimal
square into an infinitesimal Square
if under coordinate transformations of
the sigma tole plane squeezing and
mappings of the sigma toal plane if it
takes every small square into a small
square then the llas equation will be
will be unchanged in the new coordinates
so if we have some new coordinates let's
call it Sigma Prime which is a function
of Sigma and to and to Prime which are
functions of Sigma and
to if it is true that any small Sigma to
square maps into this is the sigma plane
Sigma tow plane we map it now to the
sigma Prime tow plane most mappings will
not take squares to squares they'll take
squares to something
else but there's a special class of
mappings which take squares to squares
anybody know the name of such mappings
conformal
mappings conformal mappings
now let me express it another
way if I have a transformation which
preserves
angles if all angles are
preserved then it will be a conformal
transformation it will take squares to
squares why well first first of all
let's
take the um the diagonals and map them
to the sigma to plane so to the sigma
Prime to Prime
plane there'll be little short segments
oriented in some other
direction and let's suppose that all
angles are preserved under this mapping
any angle between two curves becomes the
same angle among the sigma Prime the the
the prime plane all right then first of
all orthogonal angles here will go to
orthogonal angles here this is not true
of any old transformation it's true of
some class of Transformations the angle
preserving
Transformations now we can say something
else supposing that it's that it had
this property of taking uh um
perpendiculars in here the
perpendiculars but it stretched things
out in One Direction
in other words it made a kind of
elongated kite out of a little square
then there would be other angles which
weren't preserved these angles over here
would be
changed this angle at this corner would
not if this is a 45° angle if it
stretched the square in some way it
would not remain 4 45 de angle so
conclusion angle preserving
Transformations Preserve little squares
take little squares to little squares
yeah wouldn't that just be basically
rotational what's that wouldn't that
just be basically rotation locally it's
only a rotation but but uh but it no no
but it can it can bend the coordinates
no it's not it's not just
rotations remember we're only demanding
that
infinitesimal uh little squares remain
infinitesimal little squares but now we
can say it without in using the word
infinite
teso if the transformation has the
property that the
angle between any
intersecting pair of Curves on the sigma
tow
plane Maps into the same angle on the
sigma Prime to Prime
plane then that mapping is conformal
conformal mappings preserve not they
preserve angles but since they preserve
all angles for sufficiently small shapes
for sufficiently small shapes you can
think of the curves as being straight
lines and it's easy to prove for
sufficiently small shapes the shapes
themselves are uh are preserved sizes
are not
preserved sizes are not preserved a
small square over
here can map to a bigger Square over
here oh I didn't dra you know what I
mean can hm
sizes can be preserved sizes can be can
also be preserved in addition then we're
talking about the rotations and
translations right that's a much much
smaller class of
Transformations now here we're talking
just about the angle preserving
Transformations and they can expand and
contract uh shapes in fact they can
expand and contract differently in
different regions of the plane over here
a shape might get stretched to a bigger
shape over here a shape might get
squashed to a smaller
shape question yeah would this formal
mapping be equivalent to saying the
coordinate system is
flat nope conformally flat no I don't
know what do you mean by coordinate
system being flat you mean cartisian
that it's not curved otherwise the
angles wouldn't be preserved no no no
no where is this trick of conformal
mappings used Pro well any projection of
a map which is intended to preserve the
shape of islands continents and so forth
small
ones but doesn't care about the sizes of
things that's a conformal
mapping so the relationship between
different Maps different
projections both of which Pres OB erve
shapes but not sizes is always a
conformal
mapping yeah last week you said when we
were looking at the string uh scatter
the at the end you could you had enough
freedom
to assume that this the string when it
split again was kind of in half and is
that related to this
yeah we will
all right since you ask me I will tell
you right now what the relationship
is
okay I was going to tell you a little
bit about analytic functions but maybe
we'll come back to
that coordinate Transformations which
are defined by analytic functions of
complex variables are angle preserving
we may we may come back to
that
okay oh incidentally there is
one uh
situation where angles are not
necessarily preserved it's a curious one
um you can take
any figure with a
boundary let's say a
square a big Square now not a not an
infinite decimal square a finite size
square and map it by conformal mapping
to any shape you like but in particular
you could map it uh to a this this
doesn't look very
Square you can map it it to
a like
that so wait a minute you said that they
have to preserve angles this doesn't
look like it preserves the angles but
first of
all
uh it only preserves infinite infinitely
small shapes you can map this to this by
conformal mapping but the
corners will not go to the corners
the corners here will perhaps go to
these
points okay so conformal mappings are
tricky you can map any
shape with a boundary to any other shape
with the same boundary this is a theorem
about analytic mappings and inside the
region any small shape will map to a
shape of the same kind any small shape
here will map to a shape of the small
same kind here in the interior of the
mapping so this is something to know
that you can do some things with
changing the the shapes of boundaries of
regions okay having said that now let me
come to what the what the point
is last time we talked about strings
splitting and joining I drew a picture
for you where two strings came came in
and I indicated that by making a
slit take a ribbon make a slit down the
ribbon until that slit comes to an end
point those are two separate strings
joining at this point and making one
long
string and then continuing again after
it splits again like
that there's a one parameter family of
such splittings and joinings
characterized by the time interval or
the tow interval between this point and
that point in the end if you're
calculating a scattering amplitude you
integrate over it you get some integral
and that integral gave you the beta
function the oiler beta function or the
veneziano amplitude however you want to
call it we wrote I described it for you
last
time uh and it gives you the scattering
amplitude in string theory important
fact but uh
not really terribly Central right now
um okay what's going on in here what's
going on in here is we have a
two-dimensional space we can call it
Sigma too it is Sigma too and we have at
each point in the space we have an X Not
Just One X but several x a family of x's
X mu of Sigma and
too and they satisfy some kind of
equations in fact what kind of equations
do they satisfy
they satisfy the llas
equation now actually technically they
satisfy the wave equation but if you do
this trick and carry out the path
integrals by letting to go to
itow then the x's in here satisfy the
lass equation what does that tell you it
tells you that you can map here we have
a shape or here we have a a uh a piece
of a plane
it goes out to Infinity along here think
of it as being slit down the center
here and think of it as being slit down
the center
here what's the topology of this region
here I'll tell you what the topology of
this region is the topology of this
region is a
circle but with some special why is it a
circle um let's start at the center of a
circle and work outward with a series of
circles it's a bull ey let's start at
the center of this and work outward
I can do this in such a
way as to cover the whole Space by a
sequence of closed curves which are
isomorphic to the to the circles in
other words I have taken the bullseye
and deformed it but
without changing its topology I have
changed it into this double
strip uh with these points over here now
hm yeah it depends on what happens out
there yeah yeah right there's some
exceptional points there's some
exceptional points and the exceptional
points are the infinite end points there
and there but you can do this mapping
this mapping exists and you'll have to
remember that there were some
exceptional
points which have to
be we have to know what to do with those
exceptional points but the answer is
that
the that the um I don't know what to
call this shape what should we call it
the slit the slit strip the doubly slit
strip okay that's a mouthful Banda the
what the Band-Aid no no no no no it's
cut down the middle there so it's not
quite a Band-Aid Sports bandaid where
they oh yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
sport the sports Band-Aid shape yeah
good right good except that it's the
infinite Sports Band-Aid shape okay
that's not much better than the than the
dou slit strip the infinite Sports
Band-Aid the infinite Sports Band-Aid
can be conformally mapped conformally
mapped to the circle or to the uh to the
dis to the dis the dis is a circle is
the interior of a
circle so that means in principle we can
take the wave of equation or we can take
the llas equation or the action even of
the action of the uh of the
string the path integral for the string
the entire setup and rewrite it in a
form in which the X's all live on a unit
circle where the X's all live on a unit
circle there's something special about
these four points here where the
particles came in and went out and I'm
going to event tell you what that
special thing
is you can map it to here of course you
can map it to here but you can map it to
here without changing the form of the
equation it's still just a lass equation
the lass equation for the x's in
here is the transform of the Lao
equation for the for the for the thing
in
here okay and that's because the
conformal invariance of
the because of the conformal invari of
the pl
equation so you could set up the string
path
integral in a new
way by taking a unit
dis thinking of a set of x's which live
in the unit dis and integrating over all
ways all X's that live on this unit dis
in other words yeah I think you
understand X of Sigma and to
where Sigma and to are not
on the uh the sports Band-Aid but
they're on the
dis writing the action as the same kind
of action and path integrating over the
x's in here with some special things
going on at these four exceptional
points uh I think I won't get into what
the there's nothing very complicated
about and I will we will get to it we
will certainly get to it
it uh technically or or in the jargon is
you have to put
some um vertex operators at the uh at
the point over here but we'll come to
that all
right but you could also have stretched
that out into other shapes you could
have stretched that out into a shape
which look like
this which went off to Infinity so it
looks actually more like a scattering
process
there are many things you could have
stretched it out
into
okay
now let's take a
break let's take a
break all right
now in mapping this problem to this
problem now by this problem I mean the
problem of calculating the scattering
amplitudes you there is something that
you have to do out at these infinite
points here to set up and specify the
initial and final states of the
particles that are coming in their
momenta their particle type are they the
ground states are they the first excited
States somewhere in
here there's some input of information
that's above and beyond just saying that
there's a llao equation in here that
input of information has to do with
something or other that we do out near
the out near the ends here I'm not sure
how to draw that just some input at the
uh end flaps of the of the
Band-Aid that same input has to be put
into this
diagram we have to say what kind of
particles what is their momentum not
going to tell you exactly how to do that
at the moment I will tell you eventually
but it's some operation that you do on
each one of these points to inject in a
certain amount of momentum and some
information about the particle type okay
so keep that in mind all right now where
exactly do we put those points those
four points in this diagram it's clear
where we put them we put them out the N
flaps of the uh the
Band-Aid in this diagram it's less clear
and I will tell you what is correct in
mapping this to here you forget forget
for a moment the ends you have some
ambiguity for example you could rotate
it you can do some other things to it
but you also have enough ambiguity that
you can arbitrarily choose that there's
really only one
parameter uh in the relationship between
the four points on here one parameter
all the other it looks like there are
really several parameters you could
arbitrarily pick by rotating the angles
the position of this point but then
there would be the length or the
distance to here the angular distance to
here the angular distance to here and
the angular distance to here no uh you
can find conformal
Transformations which will move these
the boundary points around in various
ways and the end result is there is
really only up to a conformal
transformation there's only a one
parameter family of such configurations
and we could describe the parameters by
saying I'll arbitrarily choose Left
Right symmetry that's a choice and I'll
also choose up up U vertical
Symmetry and I can choose this point
over here since I've used since I've
decided to make the diagram both left
right and up down symmetric I have to
choose the other point over here over
here and over
here in a completely symmetric way but
that still allows a
freedom is one extreme
situation here's another extreme
situation what
determines where you put the
points whether it looks like this like
this or like
that the answer is the time interval
between here and here here which is also
a one parameter family of uh of
figures the time interval or really
strictly speaking the ratio of the time
interval to the uh to the separation
along here or the the time interval
between the tow interval between here
and here is the one
parameter that
governs where you put these points you
have to integrate over it just as we
integrated over the time separation this
is part of the path integral we
integrated over the time separation
between the joining and the splitting
that translates into a one parameter
integral over we can choose it in many
ways but in this case it's with this
particular setup it's a one parameter
integral over how we choose these points
my fingers aren't big enough to stretch
uh to stretch through this configuration
here but if we had two of us up here I
would move my fingers like that and you
would move your fingers like that and
then we'd spread them out and go the
other way that integral is still to be
done okay and it's that
integral when you work
out the path integral and then integrate
over the positions of the points in the
right way that's what gives you the beta
function in this language the beta
function comes from integrating the
positions of the injection points let's
call them injection points the positions
of the injection points over a one
parameter
family there are two extreme
situations one extreme
situation is this the other extreme
situation is like this in this extreme
situation the two input points and the
left are close
together in the other configuration over
here
uh this one and this one are close
together now this this these two
extremes must translate to some extremes
on the
Band-Aid it
does the extreme where the two incident
particles appear adjacent to each other
and the two outgoing particles appear
adjacent to each
other
that is the conformal mapping of the
configuration where the time interval
here is very very
long and so it looks like these two
points are much much
closer uh than uh the distance between
here and here that's the if you like the
mapping from the Band-Aid to the
circle of the
configuration where the intermediate
State lasts a long time it's a situation
that manifestly looks like two particles
coming in forming a string that vibrates
many vibrations and then goes off again
that's this limit what's the other limit
well the other limit is exactly the
other limit where the time interval is
very very
short the intermediate State lasts a
very short time
like
that and then the splitting occurs and
that's this limit over
here in these integrals in the various
integrals that you
do ah okay you can see from this
picture that there's some
symmetry that there's some
from this picture over here it's hard to
see that there's any symmetry between
these two extreme limits two physically
totally different pictures one an
intermediate State lasts a long time and
the other an intermediate State lasts a
very long short time doesn't look like
there's much symmetry but from this
picture here you see that uh that
somehow there is a symmetry that they
must be related to each other in some
way how are they related to each
other well
that's not the point though they're
related by The Interchange of what we
called last time the S variable and the
T variable remember what the S variable
was it was the sum of the four momenta
coming in squared or the center of mass
energy squared if we label these with
momenta then the S variable K1
K2 K3 K4
then the mandle stam variable the mandal
stam s
variable was
K1 plus
K2 squared and it corresponded to the
square of the center of mass
energy well let's write that it's equal
to the mandle stand s
variable this is not the action and it's
not any other s that I use tonight it's
the mandle stam s variable s and it's
also equal to the square of the center
of mass energy center of
Mass on the other hand it's quite clear
that we've done what we've done in going
from here to here if we we've
interchanged K1 plus K2 squar that's the
total energy coming in here
with what was this
K K1 plus K3 I
think K1 plus K3 and that's what we
called the T
variable that's not the center of mass
energy it's some combination of center
of mass
energy uh e Center mass s - m^ 2 time I
think 1 minus the cosine of the angle of
scattering or
something but it is just K1 plus K3 squ
where all moment are count that is
coming
in in this form it's manifestly clear
that these diagrams have symmetry
between the S Channel and T channel it's
also clear that if they have if they
describe
particles forming and decaying in the S
channel two particles coming in forming
and decaying they must also describe a
process
where the two incoming particles are
replaced Now by one incoming one
outgoing and a particle is
exchanged not not the creation and
annihilation of a
particle but an emission and
reabsorption of the other side of the
diagram so that's what was so
fascinating about these structures is
that one structure one simple structure
one integral but one basic principle was
accounting for both the S Channel and
the t- channel
particles the S Channel particles Were
Somehow associated with long diagrams
like this and the T Channel ones with
short ones but uh we don't have to
interpret we just say the integral was
symmetric under s goes to
T and
so whatever was there in the form
of s particles formed by K1 plus K2
coming together there was also T Channel
objects which were formed by K1 and K3
coming
together that was called Duality that
was the first Duality The Duality
between the S Channel and the
Channel now these days it's called
Channel Duality channel in this case
means either uh it's clear what it means
and it's called Channel Duality and it
was the first sort of at first it was a
miracle at first uh when thought about
in terms of Band-Aid diagrams there was
a miracle
that that uh there was a symmetry
between s Channel and te Channel it was
very quick that it was uh that it was
realized that this was because of
conformal
symmetry uh
uh and that you could map it to this
more symmetric
situation but at first at first sight it
just looked like a miracle that uh that
it
uh the trouble with understanding
Miracles it always has the same effect
you know you you may now understand it
but you no longer go Gaga over it in uh
when was it h
1969 yeah if you were to draw that
second one the the one that goes down I
I can understand how the top one
corresponds to the Band-Aid is there a
Band-Aid that corresponds to the second
one well yeah you could have drawn the
diagram the other
way you could have drawn it this way
would still be going horizontally well
yeah you could well yes well no time
comes in here well no no no no no no no
you could in that case you could not
have thought of time as running uh
horizontally you would have to say this
was the Deep remote past over here and
this was the Deep remote future over
here but you could have drawn it that
way for for some reason I think of the
the time that they're together being
related to the coupling constant no no
no um the time that they're together you
have to integrate
over that's something you integrate over
uh I think what you're trying to say is
that in a the probability for it to
Decay is related to the coupling
constant yeah but in either case no
matter what you still that just means
you have to put into the
integral the coupling constant and
uh but no it it uh these diagrams the
coupling constant just comes in as a
multiplicative
factor and
right okay I think uh that's enough for
tonight
for more please visit us at stanford.edu